Guide to the Nikki Van Hightower Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Nikki Van Hightower Papers
1967-1997
1997-017
Hightower, Nikki Van, 1939-
7.50 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection documents the career of Nikki Van Hightower from the time of her appointment as Women's Advocate up to, and including, her work as Harris County Treasurer.
Biographical Information:
In the course of her career Nikki Van Hightower has been Women's Advocate for the City of Houston, Moderator/Commentator at Radio Station KTRH, Executive Director of the Houston Area Women's Center, and Harris County Treasurer. She has held teaching positions at the University of Houston, Texas A & M University, Lee Community College, the University of Texas School of Public Health, and the New York Institute of Technology. She has been an outspoken activist in the women's movement and a leading proponent of equality for women in the city of Houston.
Van Hightower became involved in the women's movement while in college in the early 1970s; she continued her involvement after moving to Houston in 1975. In 1976 she was appointed to the position of Women's Advocate by Mayor Fred Hofheinz, and was responsible for "coordinating efforts to secure equal rights for women" in Houston. In this capacity she served as the city liaison for the International Women's Year National Conference, which was held in Houston in 1977, and raised public awareness of women's issues with her daily presentation of the Women's Advocate Hour on Radio Station KTRH.
Van Hightower's criticism of inequalities in city employment practices, and her feminist activities, ensured her unpopularity with City Council members. In 1977 they voted to reduce her salary to $1.00 a year in an effort to force her to abandon the role of Women's Advocate. Hofheinz countered by reinstating her as "Affirmative Action Specialist," allowing her to carry out the same job under a different name. She remained in this position until Jim McConn, who succeeded Hofheinz as mayor, fired her in March 1978.
KTRH Radio subsequently hired Van Hightower to present daily commentaries and host the call-in show Doubletalk with Ed Brandon. She was fired from the station, apparently for being too controversial, in March 1979.
By this time she was committed to working with the Houston Area Women's Center, which she helped to establish in 1977. In 1979 she became the Center's Executive Director and held that position until 1986.
In 1983, Van Hightower entered elective politics, campaigning unsuccessfully for City Council At Large Position 4. In 1986, she launched a successful campaign for Harris County Treasurer, and took office in January 1987. For the next three years she fought policies which compromised the Treasurer's control of county finances. In 1990 she was unsuccessful in her bid as Democratic Nominee for State Treasurer. She currently holds the positions of Lecturer in the Department of Political Science, and Senior Lecturer with the Health Science Center at Texas A & M University.
Throughout her career, Van Hightower received numerous honors and awards and established an impressive vita of community involvement, publications, speaking engagements, and teaching appointments. Her refusal to be intimidated by the "old boy" political network, which she viewed as a fundamental obstacle to equality and justice, enabled her to implement significant changes for the citizens of Houston.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Photographs; Speeches (documents)
Personal Name:
Hightower, Nikki Van, 1939-
Topical Term:
Politicians; Women -- Political activity -- Texas -- Houston; Women politicians; Women's rights -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Nikki Van Hightower, 1997
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
Houston Area Women's Center Videos, 1980- (http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=350)
Houston Area Women's Center Photographs, 1977- (http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=349)
Houston Area Women's Center Records, 1975-1990 (http://archon.lib.uh.edu/?p=collections/controlcard&id=351)
Toby Myers Papers (http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=470)
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the career of Nikki Van Hightower from the time of her appointment as Women's Advocate up to, and including, her work as Harris County Treasurer. It contains material dating from 1967 to 1997, with the bulk of the material dating from 1977 to 1989. Types of material within the collection include correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, speeches, commentaries, press statements, publications, diaries, photographs and clippings.
The papers were originally filed in broad subject categories which have, where possible, been retained in the eight series titles: Women's Advocate, Radio, Houston Area Women's Center, International Women's Year, Political Publicity, Speeches, Personal Files, and Clippings. In order to facilitate research, files were broken down into a more detailed topical arrangement. Folders are arranged alphabetically by title within series and sub-series. Where possible, papers are arranged chronologically within folders. When dates are consistently lacking, as with the speeches and radio commentaries, material is arranged alphabetically by title.
Van Hightower's work as Women's Advocate is particularly well documented in the collection. The papers reveal the significance of that position in relation to city government and to the fact that Houston was chosen as the site of the International Women's Year National Conference in 1977.
The papers representing Van Hightower's work at KTRH reveal the extremes of opposition and support which could be engendered by the kind of direct approach to controversial social issues which Van Hightower took in the 1970s.
Also notable are the speeches and clippings. The speeches constitute a substantial portion of the collection, revealing the range of subjects oh which Van Hightower spoke, and the extent of her community involvement. The clippings provide a valuable insight into media treatment of feminism during the 1970s and 1980s.
The Houston Area Women's Center series is the smallest in the collection. Van Hightower's work as Executive Director for the Center is more fully documented in the Houston Area Women's Center collection, also housed in the Carey C. Shuart Women's Research Collection.
Detailed List of Contents
- Women's Advocate
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains thirty-one folders. Papers date from 1973 to 1978, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1976 to 1978. The series is divided into three sub-series: General Files, Reports and Studies, and Women's Rights Coordinating Council. Of particular note are the correspondence and memoranda files, which document the particular practices and policies with which Van Hightower took issue, and the range of opposition and support she received in response. Also noteworthy are the studies on the status of women in Houston.
  - General Files
    - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Engagement Diaries, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Messages/Notes, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Miscellany, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Opponents/Supporters of Women's Advocate Position, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ordinances Affecting Women's Advocate Position, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Press Releases/Proposals Defining Women's Advocate Position, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Press Releases/Statements Supporting Women's Advocate Position, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Quarterly/Yearly Reports of Activities, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Record of Women's Advocate Achievements, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reports and Studies
    - Employee Child Care Needs - City of Houston, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Employment Rights of the Women in Houston, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Progress Report on the Status of Women in Houston, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Single Parent Seminar Program, parts 4-6, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - State of the Women in Houston Background Material, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - State of the Women in Houston, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Status of Houston Women, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Status of Women in Houston City Government as of December 31, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Texas Child Care Inc. Study, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Women's Rights Coordinating Council
    - Assorted Material, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Assorted Material, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Equal Opportunity Employment Commission, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Radio
  There are forty-five folders in this series, with two sub-series representing the two different capacities in which Van Hightower worked with Radio Station KTRH: Daily Commentaries/ Doubletalk, and Women's Advocate Hour. Material dates from 1976 to 1979. The correspondence in the first sub-series consists almost entirely of letters from listeners. Correspondence in the second sub-series relates primarily to arrangements for the show. Guests of note on the Women's Advocate Hour included Ellie Smeal, then President of the National Organization of Women, and Gloria Steinem.
  - Daily Commentaries / Doubletalk
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 15-21)
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - A, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - B, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - C, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - D, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - E, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - F, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - G, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - H, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - I-K, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - L, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - M-O, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - P, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - R, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - S, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - T, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - U, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - V-W, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Untitled, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Miscellany, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Notebook of Radio Program Topics, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Notebook of Radio Program Topics, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Notes, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Women's Advocate Hour
    - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, Questions, and Preparatory Material, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 16-19)
    - Correspondence, Questions, and Preparatory Material, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Guests A-B, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Guests C-G, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Guests H-K, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Guests L-Mac, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Guests N-O, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Guests P-S, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Open Forum, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Telephone Messages, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Houston Area Women's Center
  This series contains ten folders with material dating from 1977 to 1986. Initially, these files contained very little correspondence; correspondence and memoranda pertaining specifically to the Women's Center have since been transferred to this series from Van Hightower's personal files. The series also contains reports and publications.
  - Annual and Progress Reports, 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Center Line, 1978-1982 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Center Line, 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Community Resources For Women, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Memoranda, and Reports, 1977-1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Memoranda, and Reports, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Descriptive Planning Document, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Institute of International Education, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Miscellany, 1978-1982 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Task Force on School Violence Report, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- International Women's Year
  This series contains thirty-seven folders in three sub-series, which reflect the original arrangement: Texas Women's Meeting, Houston Conference Preparations, and National Conference. Material dates from 1976 to 1987, with the bulk of the material being from 1977. In the first sub-series, folders labeled "Committee Materials" contain papers relating to the activities of the Coordinating, Advisory, and Executive Committees of the Texas Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year Decade. Because separation of these papers would have disrupted the original order entirely, these folders contain a combination of agendas, minutes, membership lists, procedures, rules and memoranda. For the same reason, the term "correspondence" should be interpreted loosely here. Notable correspondents in this series include Judge Elizabeth Athanasakos (Presiding Officer of the National Committee on the Observance of International Women's Year), Hilary Whittaker (Conference Coordinator), and Bella Abzug (Secretariat for International Women's Year).
  - Texas Women's Meeting
    - Agendas, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Budget Proposals for International Women's Year Grant, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Committee Materials, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 21-22)
    - Coordinating Committee-Outreach, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Memoranda and Miscellany, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Messages/Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Procedural Information, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Proposal to Steering Committee for Contract Services, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Resolutions Adopted, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Summary of the Final Report by the Texas Coordinating Committee to the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Houston Conference Preparations
    - Support and Welcome Resolution Correspondence and Information, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Women in City Government Project Correspondence and Information, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Women in City Government Project Correspondence and Information, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - National Conference
    - City Brochure - Houston, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - City Brochure - San Antonio, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Conference Brochures, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
    - Correspondence and Miscellany, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Delegate/Alternate Letters, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - General Information and Rules of Order, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Houston Committee, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Manual for Planning and Conducting Meetings For Women - Revisions, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Manual for State and Territorial International Women's Year Coordinating Committees, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Messages/Notes, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Name Lists for Invitations and Reservations, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - National Women's Conference Committee 10th Anniversary Observance, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Press Releases, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Proposed National Plan of Action, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Resolutions Adopted, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Torch Relay Information, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Updates for State and National Meetings, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Political Publicity
  This series contains ten folders dating from 1983 to 1989, with the bulk of the material from 1987 to 1989. Materials include election campaign publicity material, press releases, statements, and transcripts pertaining to two issues of particular prominence: the debate over transferring duties from the County Auditor to the Treasurer, and the 25.5% pay increase which County Commissioners awarded themselves in the 1989 budget. These files originally contained clippings which have been transferred to the clippings series.
  - Annual Reports of the County Treasurer, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Campaign for City Council Correspondence and Publicity, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Campaign for County Treasurer - Publicity, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Clarification of Treasurer's Duties, 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Clarification of Treasurer's Duties, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Commissioner's Court Meeting Transcripts, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Commissioner's Court Meeting Transcripts, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Commissioner's Salary Increase, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Messages/Notes, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Miscellany, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Speeches and Presentations
  There are one hundred twenty-nine folders in this series. Although much of the material is not dated, some speeches have had dates supplied using information from Van Hightower's 1997 resume. Dates covered are 1967 to 1994. The series is divided into seven sub-series: Education, Government and Finance, History and Status of the Women's Movement, Women in Business and Political Life, Women in Crisis, Miscellaneous Subjects, and Speaking Engagement Arrangements. The first six sub-series contain full text versions and plans of speeches, presentations, statements, and testimonies. Folders also contain notes and accompanying material when applicable. Since the majority of speeches and plans were titled, they are arranged alphabetically by title in individual folders. Speeches with the same or similar titles may be foldered together. Titles of sub-series were imposed by the processor, and some assumptions had to be made about which speeches accompanying material was originally related. Untitled speeches are located at the end of the appropriate sub-series. In most cases there is no indication of the audience to which a speech was addressed. Those named include the following: American Association of University Women American Society for Public Administration Bay Area Turning Point Auxiliary Club Center for Women's Opportunities Conference for County Councils on the Status of Women First South Central Women's Studies Conference Gulf Coast Community Services Association Gulf Coast Section Society of Petroleum Engineers Houston Chapter of Hadassah Houston Independent School Board Houston Philosophical Society Houston Police Department Independent School Association of the Southwest National Council of Jewish Women National Management Association, Lockheed Northshore Rotary Club Palacios High School Rotary Club of Houston Society for Histopathologists Society for Medical Technology Texas 71st Air Force Junior R.O.T.C. Squadron Texas Association for Drug Abuse Services Inc. Texas Education Agency Texas Women's Political Caucus Texas Women's University Unitarian Universalist Fellowship of Brazos Valley United States Customs Service University of Houston Academic and Professional Women's Association Women's Economic Club
  - Education
    - 6th Annual Law School Conference - Title IX, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - A.A.U.W. Awards Banquet Keynote Address, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - B.P.W. Foundation Address, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Equal Vocational Education, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - The Hidden Curriculum, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Government and Finance
    - Harris County, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - The Impact of Federal Tax Reform on Local Government, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Political Influences on Financial Management, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Politics of Government Finance, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Texas and the Politics of Disenchantment, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - You Make A Difference, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Untitled, 1989-1991 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - The History and Status of the Women's Movement
    - Are Men for Women?, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Are Women Changing Men?, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Equal Rights Amendment, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Female/Male Equality: Dreams of the Future, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Feminist Politics, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Feminists: True Champions of the Homemaker, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - History and Philosophy of the Feminist Movement, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Houston Philosophical Society Address, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Looking Back: 20 Years of Uneven Progress in the Women's Movement, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - The Role of Women in Society, undated (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - State of the Women in Houston, undated (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - The Status of Women, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - The U.S. Constitution and Women's Rights, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - What Is Left To Be Done?, undated (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Women Against Women: Where are the Battle Lines?, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Women's Economic Agenda, undated (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Women's Issues Then and Now, undated (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Women's Movement, undated (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - The Women's Movement: Crises and Accomplishments, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Women's Suffrage, undated (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Women Today, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Untitled, 1977-1989 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Parenting
    - Child Care, undated (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Public Policy and the Single Parent Family, undated (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Statement to the Members of the Houston Independent School Board, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Testimony Before the Center for Women's Opportunities, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Personal Growth
    - The High Cost of Low Self-Esteem, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Living a Courageous Life, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Living With Success, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Maintenance of Power, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Mental Health in a Sexist Society, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Mystique of the Loner, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - The Personal to the Political, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Risk-Taking: Inventing a New Wheel, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Taking Risks, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Womanpower: How to Get it, How to Use it, and is it Worth it Anyhow?, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Women and Change, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Women and Risk-Taking, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Women in Business and Political Life
    - Aggie Democrats (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Aviation Department, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Becoming a Political Person, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Can Women Make a Difference?, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Employment Discrimination, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Establishing a Mutually Valuable Partnership With Your Boss, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Gender Gap, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - How to Be an Effective NPO Executive, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - How to Make it in a Man's World, undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - The Impact of Sex Roles and Sex Stereotyping on Female Employment in the City, undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Influencing Local Government: Pressure Group Activity, undated (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Involvement and the Professional Woman, undated (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Learning From the Women's Movement: Implications For Management, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Male/Female Sex Roles in the Workforce: Phony or Real?, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - N.A.S.A. Vendors Address, undated (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - National Management Association Lockheed Address, undated (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Networking, undated (Box 9, Folder 30)